Guide to the Martin Hayes Bickham Papers 1911-1965
University of Chicago Library
Bickham, Martin Hayes. Papers
1911-1965
3.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Martin Hayes Bickham, sociologist (University of Chicago, A.M. 1919, Ph.D. 1922). The Martin Hayes Bickham Papers consist of materials from coursework in the Sociology Department and Divinity School (1912-1922), correspondence relating to his appointment as secretary of the University of Chicago Christian Association (1911), materials related to his dissertation research (1922), correspondence with Amos Alonzo Stagg (1950s-1960s), and 1938-1939 correspondence related to his dissertation research. The collection also contains photographs and memorabilia from Bickham’s work with the Y.M.C.A. during the First World War in France.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions.
Biographical Note
Martin Hayes Bickham was born on October 7, 1880 in Churchtown, Pennsylvania. He received his A.B. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1908. He was a student in the Sociology Department at the University of Chicago from 1912-1922 and received his A.M. in 1919 and his Ph.D. in 1922. His A.M. thesis was titled “The Relations of Sociology and Religion from 1865 to 1915.” His Ph.D. thesis, under the direction of Albion Small, was titled “The Scientific Antecedents of the Sociology of Auguste Comte.”
Prior to commencing his academic work at the University of Chicago, Bickham was appointed as secretary of the University of Chicago Christian Association in 1911. During World War I, he served with the Y.M.C.A in Paris. He was also an assistant coach for Amos Alonzo Stagg at the University of Chicago for several years beginning in 1911.
Following his graduation with a Ph.D. in sociology in 1922, Bickham went on to become a practicing sociologist, conducting studies in such subjects as racism, poverty, and social life on American college campuses. He became an influential figure in urban social affairs, especially matters relating to equal opportunity, open housing and civil liberties in the Chicago area.
Martin Hayes Bickham died in Evanston, IL in 1976.
Scope Note
The Martin Hayes Bickham Papers contain 3.5 linear feet of material and cover the period from 1911 to 1965. They consist of materials from coursework in the Sociology Department and Divinity School (1912-1922), correspondence relating to his appointment as secretary of the University of Chicago Christian Association (1911), materials related to his dissertation research (1922), and correspondence with Amos Alonzo Stagg (1950s-1960s). The collection also includes 1938-1939 correspondence with the American Sociological Society and “Friends of Comte and his Work,” which refers to his dissertation research on Comte. Finally, the collection contains materials from the First World War in France—maps, tourist guide books, and other memorabilia, as well as photo postcards photographs, printed photographs, and negatives. Some of these photographic materials relate to the work of Y.M.C.A. in France after the War.
The professional papers of Martin Hayes Bickham are located at the University of Illinois Circle Campus Library. The Bickham Family Papers ca. 1760 through the 1950s comprise a separate manuscript collection in the University of Chicago Library.
The collection has been divided into four series: 1. University of Chicago Course Materials, 2. Correspondence and Papers (arranged chronologically), 3. Photographic Images, and 4. First World War Memorabilia.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Bickham Family. Papers
Albion W. Small. Papers
C. LeRoy Baldridge. Papers
Amos Alonzo Stagg. Papers
Subject Headings
Bickham, Martin Hayes; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926; Stagg, Amos Alonzo, 1862-1965; University of Chicago. Dept. of Sociology; University of Chicago. Divinity School; University of Chicago -- Societies, etc.; World War, 1914-1918; Photographs
INVENTORY
- Series I: University of Chicago Course Materials
  - Record of coursework for Master's and Ph.D. in Sociology (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bedford, Scott E. W., "History of Sociology," Autumn, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coulter, J. M., "Botany 5," Winter, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faris, Ellsworth, "Social Attitudes," Spring, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foster, George B., "History of Science and Religion," 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Foster, George B., Seminar, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Henderson, Charles R., Course 53, July-Aug., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Keubler, William E., "Social Psychology," Winter, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - King, Henry C., "Ethics of Jesus," July, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mathews, Shailer, "Bible," Jan., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mathews, Shailer, "Church and Society," Autumn, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mathews, Shailer, "Sunday Morning Bible," Winter, 1913; MHB term papers (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mathews, Shailer, "Social and Ethical Teaching of Jesus," Winter, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mead, George H., "Advanced Social Psychology," Winter, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Modern Industry," notes for course (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Schevill, Ferdinand, "History of Civilization," Autumn, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Small, Albion W., "Conflict of Classes," Spring, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Small, Albion W., "Elements of Sociology," Autumn, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Small, Albion W., "History of Sociology 1800-1865," Winter, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Small, Albion W., "History of Sociology 1865 to present," Winter, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Small, Albion W., "Introduction to Sociology," n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Small, Albion W., Seminar, 1915-1916, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Thomas, William I., "Social Origins," Spring, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence and Papers
  - University of Chicago Christian Association, 1911, Charles W. Gilkey to MHB, June 5 MHB to Gilkey, June 6 E.C. Carter to MHB, June 7 Gilkey to MHB, L. Wilbur Messer to MHB, June 11 Telegram, Messer (by Goodspeed) to MHB, June 13 John M. Coulter to MHB, June 14 Wm. J. Parker to MHB, June 14 F. A. Crosby to MHB, June 15 MHB to Parker, June 15 MHB to Coulter, June 15 Goodspeed to MHB, June 28, encl. "Outline for YMCA work at the University of Chicago," "The Young Men's Christian Association of the University of Chicago, Mid-Year Bulletin, January 1911" C. H. B. Goodspeed to MHB, June 13 MHB to Goodspeed, June 14 MHB to Coulter, June 28 MHB to Goodspeed, June 28 Coulter to MHB, June 30 Goodspeed to MHB (with note from Gilkey appended), June 30 Carter to MHB, July 1 Messer to MHB, July 1 MHB to Messer, July 3 MHB to Goodspeed, n.d. MHB to Gilkey, July 3 MHB to Coulter, July 5 "Delegates to the Kansas City Volunteer Convention," December 31, 1913 to January 4, 1914. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dissertation research, 1921, "Syllabus of Proposed Dissertation," n.d. Small to MHB, n.d. Small to MHB, May 31 Small to MHB, June 16 Faris to MHB, July 15 Small to MHB, July 27 Curriculum vitae, MHB Tuition receipts Small to MHB, Dec 29, 1921 Small to MHB, n.d. Small to MHB, n.d. Small to MHB, n.d. Small to MHB, n.d. "Statement of the Problem" U of C press, thesis abstracts order form, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Sociological Society, Comtean Centenary, 1938-1939, MHB to Frank H. Hankins, Pres. American Sociological Society, Dec. 14, 1938, encl. MHB dissertation abstract H. A. Phelps to MHB, Dec 15, 1938 Hankins to MHB, Dec 16, 1938 MHB to Hankins, Dec 21, 1938 Hankins to MHB, Dec 23, 1938 MHB to Judith Waller, National Broadcasting Co., Dec 27, 1938 MHB to Hankins, Dec 27, 1938 MHB to Allen Miller, University Broadcasting Co., Dec 29, 1938 "Program of the Twenty-third Annual Meeting of the American Sociological Society," Detroit, Dec 28-30, 1938 "Historians hear why Americans think as they do," Chicago Daily Tribune, Dec 29, 1938 Earle Eubank to MHB, Jan 18, 1939 MHB to Eubank, Jan 21, 1939 Grace Curran, National Broadcasting Company, to MHB, April 3, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Society of Friends of Auguste Comte and His Work, 1938-1939, Nicholas Murray Butler to A. P. Edger, July 21, 1938 Philip L. Seman, General Director, Jewish People's Institute of Chicago, to MHB, Jan 29, 1939 MHB to Seman, Feb 3, 1939 Seman (by Helen Brody) to MHB, Feb 3, 1939 Seman to MHB, April 3, 1939 with trans. copy letter from Auguste Paul Edger to Seman MHB to Seman, May 1, 1939 Seman to MHB, May 2, 1939 Seman to MHB, May 3, 1939, with copy letter from Robert E. Scheider to Seman, and trans. copy letter Scheider to Edger Edger to MHB, May 15, 1939, with conference program (French) F. Fagnot to MHB, May 23, 1939 Seman (by Brody) to MHB, May 30, 1939, with letter from Edger to Seman Brody for Seman to MHB, with letter from Fagnot to Seman, June 1, 1939 MHB to Cecil H. Desch, June 5, 1939 MHB to Otto Baier, June 5, 1939 MHB to Fagnot, June 5, 1939 MHB to Edger, June 5, 1939 MHB to Seman, June 5, 1939 MHB to Robert Ross, June 5, 1939 Desch to MHB, July 9, 1939 Baier to MHB, June 15, 1939 Baier to MHB, July 13, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous circulars, societies, Undated list of names Circulars, Union Internationale de Pacifistes Patriotes: Jan 15, 1933, n.d., June 3, 1934, March 8, 1936, Nov 28, 1938 Circulars, Société des Amis d' Auguste Comte et de Son Oeuvre two undated circulars with envelopes (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Offprints, Otto Baier, "In Memoriam-Sydney Style," 23 February 1930 Frank E. Hartung, "The Sociology of Positivism," Science and Society 8(4) Fall 1944 Frank E. Hartung, "The Social Function of Positivism," Philosophy of Science 12(2) April 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - MHB papers and correspondence, MHB, "The Scientific Antecedents of the Sociology of Auguste Comte," The University of Chicago Abstracts of Theses, Humanistic Series, Volume 1 MHB, "Comte's 'Physique Sociale,' The Introductory Treatise in the Modern Social Construction Movement," submitted to Dr. Small, Nov. 1921, 2 typescript copies MHB, "A Comtean Centenary;Comte's formulation of his Sociological Concepts," 1922 draft with pasted excerpts of dissertation, with 1965 note "A Comtean Centenary," [American Journal of] Sociology, 1922, based on materials collected by MHB and rewritten by A. W. Small, typescript copy Don Martindale to MHB, with MHB dissertation abstract and "Comtean Centenary," April 13, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Amos Alonzo Stagg Correspondence and Memorabilia, Stagg to MHB, Sept 4, 1959 Stagg to MHB, Jan. 6, 1960 Stagg to MHB, Aug. 16, 1961 Stella Stagg to MHB, June 15, 1962 Paul Stagg, n.d. Newpaper articles, Stagg's 97th and 100th birthday Clipping, Stagg scholarship fund Admission slip, signed by Stagg Photo of Stag (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series III: Photographic Images
  - Subseries 1: Commercial photo postcards
    - Chateau-Thierry, "Grande Guerre 1914-1918" (14 cards) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Gisors (13 cards) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Reims (10 cards) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Ruins of Soissons after 2nd invasion, (booklet of 24 plus 3 duplicates) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Soissons (10 cards) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Verdun, "La Guerre 1914-1918," (booklet of 20, some detached) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Ypres (11 cards, some in booklet) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Ruins of Ypres" (10 cards) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Misc., Paris and Juvigny (2 cards) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Brest, sent by MHB to wife and daughters, Aug 18, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - rec'd by MHB., Tokyo, F. Torell to MHB in Illinois, Feb 25, 1919 Dijon, E. B. Lane to MHB in Illinois, March 8, 1919 Paris, Flora Delahoyle to MHB at YMCA in Paris, n.d. Chateau de Peyriu, May H. Emerson and Ethel C. Mackey to MHB, Aug. 7, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Postcards (non-commercial, mainly from MHB negatives)
    - "M.H. Bickham, Regional Director, YMCA Paris Region at the grave of Arthur Vandeveer Savage at Mezy-sur-Marne, Memorial Day 1919" [negative, Folder 44] (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "M. H. Bickham...Mezy-sure-Marne" [negative, Folder 45] (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "The Grave of Arthur Vandeveer Savage, member of the National Committee of Council, Student Department, YMCA, USA, decorated on Memorial Day, 1919..." [negative, Folder 45] (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Memorial Day services 1919 at Ploisy near Soissons..." (2 photos) [negative, Folder 46] (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Memorial Day services 1919 at the American Cemetery, Seringes near Fere-en-Tardenois" [negative, Folder 44] (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Scene on the banks of the Marne at Mezy near Chateau Thierry where Arthur Vandeveer Savage and a platoon of Americans prevented the crossing of the Germans, July 15, 1918" [negative, Folder 47] (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Car of M. H. Bickham, Regional Director, Paris Region of YMCA in the center of Fismes..." (2 photos) [negatives, Folders 48, 49] (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Front of the Cathedral at Reims showing the effect of German fire. Car of M. H. Bickham standing in front" [negative, Folder 50] (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Remains of the church of St. John des Vignes at Soissons (3 photos) [negatives, Folder 51, 52] (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Jewish graves, at [Borry?] near St. Orientin", "American cemetery just outside of [Peronne?]" "American cemetery at Bellean Woods" [negative, Folder 53] "Old church at Long Pont near Soissons...where 2nd Division drove through July 18, 1918" (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "5/5/19, MHB on Hinderburg Line near Laffaux..." [negative, Folder 54], "5/5/19, Photograph of French cemetery at Loffaux..." [negative, Folder 55] "On the ridges above Soissons, MHB looking onto valley" [negative, Folder 56] "On the ridge above Soissons" [negative, Folder 57] "5/5/19, village church in [Fere-en-Tarder Nois?] after the bombardment..." [negative, Folder 58] (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 3: YMCA copies of prints
    - "Ethel S. Mackey, Mary H. Emerson, Marjorie Clinton, picking apple blossoms to decorate a [?] on Mother's Day, May 1919", "Ethel S. Mackey-soprano; Mary Hopkins Emerson-accompanist, Marjorie Clinton-reader, Dr. S. M. McGill-speaker [?] in Soissons" (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Two women boxing, Group photograph Inside tent "YMCA Camp Joinville, [Maise?] 1919: one of our tents" Red Cross postcard, "YMCA Brussels..." (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Student-Secretaries Summer School, Lake Geneva, Wis., 1919", "Students Life Work Meeting Lake Geneva, Wis., 1919" (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 4: Photographic prints (5" x 7" except noted)
    - Parade going by YMCA, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Gimetiére 'Americain' suresnes", Chateau-Thierry Two men on German tank (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Reims, 9 photos (1 is an aerial view) (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - German officers looking at map, Monument, Aix Morts pour la Patre (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1-4, "Party of sailors at the Champs des Mars under the Eiffel Tower ready to leave on a sightseeing trip around Paris, Aug 1919," Ernest Wardavoir, photographer. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Grave of Quentin Roosevelt," Spring 1919, 5" x 7" [negatives, Folder 59-60] (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Remains of church at Missy-au-Bois near Soissons," 2 prints, 5" x 7" [negatives, Folder 61] (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Memorial Day services 1919 at Ploisy near Soissons, 1919, 5 prints, 5" x 7" [negatives, Folder 62-63] (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 3 1/2" x 3 1/2," except unlabeled, "Missy aux Bois G.R.S. men marching into Ploisy cemetery" "Dr. S. M. McGill leading Memorial Day Services, Ploisy cemetery..." "Soissons YMCA" "Refugees" "G.R.S. men at [Fisuies], Ethel S. Mackey, Mary H. Emerson" "4 [trowels?] in action, G.R.S. at [Fere-eu-Tardenois]" "G.R.S. men at Torcy, Ethel S. Mackey, Mary H. Emerson" unlabeled (5" x 4") (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Prison de la Roquette, during an Entertainment" (3 prints, 5" x 4") (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 9 prints, 3" x 4 3/4", "Hindenberg line" "Ft. Pomfelle" "Heart of Fismes" "Bellean Wood Cemetery" "Cathedral at Soissons" "Soissons, Miss Bain and Mrs. Hill" "'Y' at Soissons" "'Y' at Soissons," "'Y' at Rheins" (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 6 prints, 3 1/2" x 2 1/2", "1. Gen Paul B. Malone, speaker; 2. Miss Helen King, regional Women's work Director" "Memorial Day Party, 1919" "At Brest" 3 photos taken by E. B. Lane given to MHB (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Cemetery at Sorilly...," 3" x 4", "Grave no. 177, Edward K. Hyman of Churchtown PA," 3" x 4" (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - 20 prints, 23/4" x 11/4" [negatives, Folder 43] (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Roosevelt's grave, 2 prints, 21/4" x 21/2 " [negatives, Folder 59-60] (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Church at Missy-au-Bois, 3 prints, 21/4" x 21/2 " [negatives, Folders 61] (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - 6 prints, 21/4" x 5" strips [negatives, Folders 65-70 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Subseries 5: Negatives
    - 21 negatives [some printed, Folder 39] (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Subseries 6: Glass negatives
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 12, 16] (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 13, 14] (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 15] (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 17] (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 18] (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 19] (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 20] (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 21] (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Printed as postcards in collection, [Folder 22] (Box 3, Folder 54-58)
    - Printed as photos in collection, [Folder 31, 40] (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
    - Printed as photos in collection, [Folder 32, 41] (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Printed as photos in collection, [Folder 33] (Box 3, Folder 62-64)
    - Printed as photos in collection, [Folder 42], Folders 71-74: Not printed in collection (Box 3, Folder 65-70)
- Series IV: First World War Memorabilia
  - Bookmarks (3), Berger-Levrault, Éditeurs, Booklet," Alsace and Lorraine Desire to Remain French," 1918, in French and English, 32 pp (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Map of the Western Theatre of War," National Geographic Society, folded, Map, "Western Front at a Glance," American Expeditionary Forces, Young Men's Christian Association, booklet, 28 pp Notes, inserted into "Western Front" map (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Map, "The Western Theater of the European War," B. Barrecchia, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Booklet (5 copies), "Chateau Thierry; A friendly guide for American Pilgrims to the Shrines between the Marne and the Vesle," Seargeant Alexander Woollcott with Sketches by Private C. LeRoy Baldrige [note; Baldrige was at U of C, contemporary with Bickham] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Conquest and Kultur; Aims of the Germans in their own words," compiled by W. Notestein and E. Stoll, issued by Committee on Public information, Jan. 1918 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Illustrated Michelin Guides to the battlefields, "Bataille de la Marne-II. Les Marais de Saint-Gond; Coulommiers, Provins, Sézanne," Guides Michelin, 1917, 118 pp, French "Bataille de la Marne-III. La Trouée de Revigny; Chalons-Vitry-Bar-le-duc," Guides Michelin, 1918, 109 pp, French (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Michelin Guides, "Battle-fields of the Marne, 1914-I. The Ourco; Chantilly-Senlis-Meaux," Michelin Guides, Paris, 1917, 118 pp, English "Lille; Avent et Pendant la Guerre," Michelin, 1919, 63 pp, French "Soissons; Avent et Pendant la Guerre," Michelin, 1919, 63 pp, French (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "La Fete de la Victorire," L'illustration, 19-26 July 1919, illustrated magazine, 18 pp (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - France and America material, 1917-1919, "Programme; France-Amérique Théatre Sarah Bernhard," 29 April 1919, under auspices of A.E.F. and Y.M.C.A, French "From La Fayette to Pershing," illustrated booklet, French and English "Message from French Mothers to American Mothers," Mother's Day 1919, French and English "Matinée Franco-Américaine organisée...la celebration du Mother's Day," 1919, French (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "L'effort Français; Pendant la Guerre," two issues, one on military effort, one on industry, agriculture, transportation, and aid organizations (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Atlas of the World War, [1919], Dangerfield Printing, London (Box 5, Folder 4)